<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<?modxslt-stylesheet type="text/xsl" method="http" 
	href="${xsltRoot}/translator.xsl" 
	media="screen and ! $GET[format]" 
	alternate="no" title="For any web browser" 
	charset="ISO-8859-1"?>

<?xml-stylesheet 
	type="text/xsl" 
	method="http" 
	href="xslt/sdope/docbook.xsl"
	media="screen" alternate="no" 
	title="Per l'utibrowser" charset="ISO-8859-1"?>
	
<!--
   mod-xslt - Copyright (C) 2002, 2003 Carlo Contavalli 
 			 <ccontavalli at masobit.net> -->


<article xmlns="http://www.masobit.net/ns/sdope/1.0">
  <articleinfo>
    <title>About <bf>mod-xslt2</bf></title>  

  <author>
    <firstname>Carlo</firstname>
    <surname>Contavalli</surname>
    <affiliation>
      <address>
        <email>ccontavalli at masobit.net</email>
      </address>
    </affiliation>
  </author> 
  </articleinfo>

  <para>                                                 
    <bf>mod-xslt2</bf> is a server side module able to apply stylesheets
    to xml data on the fly. mod-xslt2 as it is today is almost a complete
    rewrite of the original mod-xslt2 written by Philipp Dunkel, with
    many new features added and a complete code clean up. <bf>mod-xslt2</bf>
    is <bf>Free Software</bf> and is released under the terms of the
    <bf>GPL</bf> and anybody is welcome to join its development.
  </para> 

  <para>
    <bf>mod-xslt2</bf> is able to:
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>parse <bf>dynamically generated xml</bf> provided by cgi 
        scripts or server side languages, like <bf>perl</bf> or <bf>php</bf>.</listitem>
      <listitem>use a <bf>full featured language</bf> based on PIs to choose 
      	which stylesheet to use, language that can make use of
	headers provided by the client, <bf>GET</bf> parameters and
	<bf>regular expressions</bf></listitem>
      <listitem>parse external <bf>DTDs</bf> and use the defaults therein 
      	provided</listitem>
      <listitem>fetch stylesheets or external entities from other
      	<bf>dynamic pages</bf>, http or ftp urls without creating the potential 
	of deadlocks and <bf>avoiding most of the dangerous conditions</bf></listitem>
      <listitem>set the <bf>mime type</bf> of the transformation result as
      	told by the xslt</listitem>
      <listitem>let the xslt access <bf>GET parameters</bf> or   
      	<bf>modify the headers</bf> returned back to the browser</listitem>
      <listitem>provide a set of <bf>standard compliant</bf> functions 
        allowing you to keep your xslt or xml files <bf>compatible</bf>
	with any xslt processor, even when using <bf>mod-xslt2</bf> enhanced
	features</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    At time of writing, <bf>mod-xslt2</bf> works with <bf>Apache 1.3</bf>
    and <bf>Apache 2.{0,1,2}</bf>. However, it provides an <bf>API</bf>
    based on an external library that should make it easy to port 
    <bf>mod-xslt2</bf> to <bf>any other web server</bf>. Work is under way to provide 
    a <bf>Proxy</bf> translator, a <bf>CGI</bf> handler, and many
    more features.
  </para>
</article>	
