<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<?modxslt-stylesheet type="text/xsl" method="http" href="${xsltRoot}/translator.xsl" 
	media="screen and ! $GET[format]" alternate="no" title="For any web browser" charset="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" method="http" href="xslt/sdope/docbook.xsl"
	media="screen" alternate="no" title="For any web browser" charset="ISO-8859-1"?>
	
<!--
   mod-xslt - Copyright (C) 2002, 2003 Carlo Contavalli 
 			 <ccontavalli at masobit.net> -->


<article xmlns="http://www.masobit.net/ns/sdope/1.0">

  <articleinfo>
    <title>Download <bf>mod-xslt2</bf></title>  

  <author>
    <firstname>Carlo</firstname>
    <surname>Contavalli</surname>
    <affiliation>
      <address>
        <email>ccontavalli at masobit.net</email>
      </address>
    </affiliation>
  </author> 
  </articleinfo>

  <para>                                                 
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink url="../software/snapshots.xml">CVS Snapshots</ulink></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  CVS contains the latest versions of mod-xslt2 sources. Every time an update is 
	  completed, a new feature is added or a bug is corrected and the code needs to be 
	  tested, a snapshot of the CVS is taken and a .tar.gz containing it is released. 
	  Follow the link above to download the latest CVS snapshot.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink url="../software/releases.xml">Standard Releases</ulink></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  Once a snapshot has been tested for a while and no dangerous bugs are found,
	  the snapshot becomes a new mod-xslt2 standard release, otherwise the bugs are
	  corrected and a new snapshot is taken, until there is a new version of mod-xslt2
	  ready. Follow the link above to download the latest mod-xslt2 release.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink url="../software/testing.xml">Testing Suite</ulink></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  Every time a new snapshot is taken, mod-xslt2 needs to be tested. 
	  In order to simplify the task of testing and to verify
	  conditions that created problems to previous versions of mod-xslt2, a 
	  testing suite has been written. At time of writing, the suite is mainly to use
	  to developers since not enough effort has been put in making it portable
	  or easy to use under most conditions. Help is welcome in improving it.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term><ulink url="../doc/documentation.xml">Documentation</ulink></term>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	  Any mod-xslt2 version is released with its own documentation. Following
	  the link above, you can access or download the latest mod-xslt2 documentation 
	  in any of the many provided formats.
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </varlistentry>

    </variablelist>
  </para> 
</article>	
