<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<?modxslt-stylesheet type="text/xsl" method="http" href="${xsltRoot}/translator.xsl" 
	media="screen and ! $GET[format]" alternate="no" title="For any web browser" charset="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" method="http" href="../xslt/docbook.xsl"
	media="screen" alternate="no" title="For any web browser" charset="ISO-8859-1"?>
	
<!--
   mod-xslt - Copyright (C) 2002, 2003 Carlo Contavalli 
 			 <ccontavalli at masobit.net> -->


<article xmlns="http://www.masobit.net/ns/sdope/1.0">

<articleinfo>
  <title>About this site</title>  
  <author>
    <firstname>Carlo</firstname>
    <surname>Contavalli</surname>
    <affiliation>
      <address>
        <email>ccontavalli at masobit.net</email>
      </address>
    </affiliation>
  </author> 

<!--  <abstract><para>
....................
  </para></abstract> -->
</articleinfo>

  <para>  
  Unless otherwise specified, permission is granted to copy, distribute 
  and or modify a copy of every document or page provided on this internet 
  site under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or
  any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with no
  Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts and no Back-Cover Texts.
  </para>

  <para>
  Any program code, source code or software provided on this site or in any
  document available on this site, unless otherwise specified, should be
  considered free software. You can redistribute it and/or modify it under
  the terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software
  Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any
  later version.
  </para>

  <para>
  Everything provided on this site is distributed in the hope that it will
  be useful, but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
  MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU General
  Public License for more details.
  </para>

  <para>
  A copy of the GNU General Public License can be found following this
  link; if not, write to the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 675 Mass Ave,
  Cambridge, MA 02139, USA or contact &lt;ccontavalli at masobit.net&gt;.
  </para>
</article>	
