<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1" standalone="no"?>
<?modxslt-stylesheet type="text/xsl" method="http" href="${xsltRoot}/translator.xsl" 
	media="screen and ! $GET[format]" alternate="no" title="For any web browser" charset="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" method="http" href="../xslt/docbook.xsl"
	media="screen" alternate="no" title="For any web browser" charset="ISO-8859-1"?>
	


<!--
   mod-xslt - Copyright (C) 2002, 2003 Carlo Contavalli 
 			 <ccontavalli at masobit.net> -->

<article xmlns="http://www.masobit.net/ns/sdope/1.0">

<articleinfo>
  <title>Join us / TODO for the next releases</title>  
  <author>
    <firstname>Carlo</firstname>
    <surname>Contavalli</surname>
    <affiliation>
      <address>
        <email>ccontavalli at masobit.net</email>
      </address>
    </affiliation>
  </author> 
</articleinfo>

  <para>  
    Any help in further developing mod-xslt is welcome, just mail me
    (&lt;ccontavalli at masobit.net&gt;) or let your voice be heard
    on one of the mailing lists. We are actually working for the next 
    releases to include:
    <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>complete apache2 support - needs to be tested and need to
    	compile in deadlock detection code.</listitem>
      <listitem>cacheing - can be implemented for parsed .xml files,
      	parsed .xsl files, and for the whole result. Most of mod-xslt
	was written with the idea, some time, to add a cacheing layer.
      </listitem>
    <listitem>update the makefiles, in order to get the updated documentation
    	in the package, both in html, xml and pdf format.</listitem>
    <listitem>cgi, proxy - add support for more web servers. The proxy SAPI
    	would make it easyer to handle cacheing.</listitem>
    <listitem>more .xslt extensions - to allow quering web server variables
    	using XPath.</listitem>
    <listitem>more .xslt web integration - it would be nice to add .xslt extensions
    	to allow stylesheets to make GET and POST subrequests or to have a 
	better control over web server internals.</listitem>
    <listitem>external parsers - at time of writing, most of the browsers do not
    	support .svg or other xml based formats. It would be nice to add a xslt 
	extension and to allow mod-xslt to call external commands to handle particular
	kinds of namespaces. For example, to handle the svg namespace, it could
	call a command to convert svg to png and insert the image in the output
	document. I have some ideas about this, but we should be really
	careful about how we add support for this.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <para>
    <bf>To report a bug</bf>, just drop a mail in one of the mod-xslt mailing lists. You
    don't have to be subscribed.
  </para>
</article>	
