<!DOCTYPE Article PUBLIC "-//Davenport//DTD DocBook V3.0//EN">

<Article>

<ArtHeader>

<Title>Patches for libxslt/libxml</Title>
<AUTHOR>
  <FirstName>Carlo Contavalli</FirstName>
</AUTHOR>

<Abstract>
<Para>
This document describes a couple patches to apply to libxml and libxslt that could be useful to improve mod-xslt2 overall
performance and reliability, even if their absence does not compromise mod-xslt2 usability.
</Para>

</Abstract>

</ArtHeader>

<Sect1>
<Title>License and Copyright</Title>
<Para>
This document is Copyright (C), Carlo Contavalli 2002-2008.
</Para>

<Para>
Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this document under the
terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version 1.1 or any later version
published by the Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no
Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of this license
can be found at http://www.commedia.it/ccontavalli/license/FDL/en/index.html.
</Para>
</Sect1>

<Sect1>
<Title>libxml - libxml.setglobalstate.diff</Title>

<Para>
The setglobalstate patch allows an application
to make use of the internal ``xmlGetGlobalState''
function provided by libxml2 and adds 
and adds a ``xmlSetGlobalState''.
</Para>

<Para>
libxml makes use of many global variables kept
in a task specific area (when multithreading
is enabled) to avoid race conditions with other
threads. However, this is not enough for mod-xslt:
many apache modules share the same thread of execution
and thus share the same ``task specific'' libxml
data. To avoid interactions with other modules
using libxml, mod-xslt saves the global execution
state and restore it for each processed request.
The process of ``storing'' and ``restoring'' is
in facts a ``copy'' of a memory area (using memcpy).
However, libxml internally uses a much more efficient
mechanism that would allow mod-xslt to ``store'' and
``restore'' a single pointer on most POSIX systems (using
POSIX threads).
</Para>

<Para>
The highlited patch allows an application (like mod-xslt) 
to make use of those functions improving overall performance.
</Para>

<Para>
The patch is automatically detected by mod-xslt ``configure''
and should not cause any harm to other applications.
</Para>

</Sect1>

<Sect1>
<Title>libxslt - libxslt.genericerror.diff</Title>

<Para>
Internally, libxslt calls ``xsltGenericError'' to 
signal an error to the application making use of the
library.
</Para>

<Para>
However, sometimes, ``xsltGenericError'' gets called
by libxslt with the arguments of the function 
``xsltGenericDebug'' instead of its own, causing
a SEGFAULT in mod-xslt (which doesn't expect
the wrong arguments to be passed - it would cause
a SEGFAULT on most applications).
</Para>

<Para>
Those ``xsltGenericError'' calls should never be
reached in the normal path of execution of the library
and of an application. However, it came out that they
are sometimes reached, usually due to bugs in libxml2
or in the xslt handlers set by mod-xslt (quite unlikely :).
</Para>

<Para>
A sort of harmless ``parachute'' has been employed in
mod-xslt to detect this situation <Emphasis remap="bf">most</Emphasis> of the
times. However, this mechanism doesn't guarantee
the error will be avoided <Emphasis remap="bf">all</Emphasis> the times.
</Para>

<Para>
To completely avoid this problem, you should patch the
library with the provided .diff (or use the configure
parameter described below).
</Para>

<Para>
The patch was created by running something like:

<Screen>
find . -type f -name '*.c' |xargs perl -pi -e \
's/xsltGenericError\(xsltGenericDebugContext/xsltGenericError\(xsltGenericErrorContext/'
</Screen>

from the libxslt source tree.
</Para>

<Sect2>
<Title>configure - --enable-libxslt-hack</Title>

<Para>
Another solution to patching the library
is to use ``--enable-libxslt-hack''. Enabling
this option to configure, mod-xslt will be
configured to setup a fake ``debug'' error
function, which uses the same parameters
as the standard error functions.
</Para>

<Para>
That way, the problem is completely avoided
without needing any further action.
</Para>

<Para>
Note, however, that by enabling this option
you enable libxslt debugging facilities,
which may potentially slow down the parsing.
</Para>

</Sect2>

</Sect1>

<Sect1>
<Title>libxslt - libxslt.fallback.diff</Title>

<Para>
During debugging, it came out that most
of those errors that used the wrong ``arguments''
were triggered by placing a ``&lt;fallback&gt;''
tag in the wrong position.
</Para>

<Para>
When such a tag is found, ``libxslt'' will 
print an error message due to the fact it
reaches an unexpected position in the code.
</Para>

<Para>
However, if you use extension tags provided
by mod-xslt and the fallback handler, you will
see quite a bounce of these errors. If the
library was not patched with libxslt.genericerror.diff
or mod-xslt not compiled with ``--enable-libxslt-hack'',
then each of these error would cause a SEGFAULT
(however, this is not my fault), otherwise, an annoying
warning is outputted in the logs.
</Para>

<Para>
To avoid this warning filling the logs, you can
apply libxslt.fallback.diff, which, conforming
with ``REC-xslt-19991116.html&num;fallback'' will make
libxslt ignore the presence of such a tag.
</Para>

<Sect2>
<Title>configure - --enable-fallback-wraparound</Title>

<Para>
Another solution to patching the library is to
compile mod-xslt passing ``--enable-fallback-wraparound''
as an argument to configure.
</Para>

<Para>
Enabling this option will cause some more code
to be compiled in mod-xslt. This code will take care
of ``stripping down'' the &lt;fallback tags from ``legal''
positions made illegal by mod-xslt usage of the library.
</Para>

<Para>
Eg, the patch solves the problem once and forever.
This option solves the problem when it is triggered
by mod-xslt, which means every time a &lt;fallback
tag is found inside a mod-xslt extension tag.
</Para>

</Sect2>

</Sect1>

</Article>
